This week I'm going to make a luxury
sweet cream ice cream base. Turn that
into a black forest ice cream that is
just going to be amazing. And I'm going
to show you how to balance that recipe
on that [music] scoopulator ice cream
calculator that I showed you last week.
Loads of people wanted to have another
video on that ice cream calculator
scoop.
Um, so that's what we're going to do
today. I went through a lot of different
iterations of Black Forest ice cream and
I focused down onto a super easy but
very luxurious sweet cream ice cream
base. We're going to do a finely chopped
chocolate addin very much like Handal's
Belgian chocolate and then we're going
to do a cherry swirl using canned
cherries. So, got my homemade Starbucks.
Let's dig in to the calculator.
Here we go. We're on Skip Peator. This
is the opening website. Very much like
you saw last time. We're going to dig
straight in with a standard ice cream
base, general ice cream target profile.
We're not going to use any of the other
ones. Now, I'm going to aim towards 14
to 15% fat here. And I'm going to reduce
the sugar by using alulose. So, first
let's add our cream. This is obviously
there's lots of different variations. If
you're in the US, use heavy cream. If
you're in the UK, go all the way down
the bottom and you will see double
cream. The two different variations.
Actually, it's there's like a dozen
different variations of double cream,
but 50 and 48. Perfect. Whipping cream.
This is my whipping cream. Like I said,
33% fat. If yours is different and it's
not on the list, just add it. It's
really easy. Next, we're going to add
the milk. And this is whole milk that
I'm adding here, but you can see there's
a long, long list. Choose the one that
you want to use. So, there we go. 3.2%
2% fat, 3.25%, but it it's, you know,
close enough. Um, sugar. Now, if you
just start typing sugar, you see loads
of different variations, but you
actually just want to choose the type of
sugar that you want here. Granulated
sugar. Now, if I were to go granulated
sugar, we can add dextrose and the likes
as well. But I I kind of want this to be
maybe a lighter sugar ice cream. So, I'm
going to use alulose.
this recipe I'm going to add a little
bit of glucose and that's going to
change the texture slightly. Glucose
corn syrup, all corn syrup is glucose
excluding high fructose corn syrup.
That's a different thing altogether.
Let's add some numbers in and get
started. 500 g of our cream and our
milk, 150 g of alulose, 15 g of glucose
syrup, and then we're going to add a
stabilizer in here cuz the solids are
going to be a bit low because we're
using alulose. So our relative sweetness
that's kind of that's deceiving slightly
by because we're using alos but our
solids as we can see 36.7
uh 36% fat are really a little bit low
but our milk solids non-fat needs to be
high. So here we go. We got our fat
percentage pretty much where I want to
be. This is the top end of where I want
to be. 15% fat. Sweet cream needs to be
luxurious. So we need it to be high fat
with good texture and balance. The
solids are a little bit low. I like my
solids to be at 40%.
That that is pretty much where I try and
get all my solids recipes, all my ice
cream recipes solids content to be
around 40%. It's a really really good
base point. But obviously because we're
using alulos, the high effect on
freezing point means we can't put as
much in. So we we balance that with a
bit of stabilizer. That stabilizer will
increase the viscosity of this base.
That in turn helps us create a
perception of higher solids content.
Higher solids content also help that
freezing point. So it's quite important.
Solids content is quite important in ice
cream. The lower your solids content,
the higher the ice crystal formation is
going to be. The larger those ice
crystals themselves will grow. So we
don't want that. We need to balance this
out to make sure that it's kind of, you
know, got that luxurious mouth feel. the
relative sweetness because we're using
alos. I'm not sure this is actually
doing a particularly good job, but alo
is 70% as sweet as normal table sugar.
So sucrose um glucose syrup is not very
sweet. It's generally you buy something
around 40de in a store which is de means
dextro dextrose equivalent. Um but it's
it's not particularly sweet. So it
doesn't increase the sweetness that
much. But actually, we don't want a
particularly sweet ice cream here. We're
going to add chocolate into it, which
will carry a sweetness level depending
on what chocolate we use. And we're
going to add in that cherry swirl, too.
That's going to be nice and sweet to cut
through this ice cream. So, we've got a
less sweet ice cream with sweeter
add-ins. Don't go too crazy with the
with the high sugar ice cream if you're
adding high sugar add-ins. So, as you
can see, we we're playing with the with
the amounts until we kind of get to
where we want to be. Now, we can look at
our evaporation settings. Now, I'm not
sure this bit this bit is maybe a little
bit misleading.
So, specify evaporation. We're going to
cook this off. It says here cooking to
eight cooking to 85C
will lose four to 5% of its weight. Now,
that is not particularly accurate
statement because if you take your base
and you heat it up incredibly fast, then
you will lose around 2%. If you leave it
up there and you cook it out completely,
then you can lose up to 10% of weight.
So, this is a generalized statement. I
take that with a pinch of salt. Here we
go. We got our scoopability right down
in the middle, which is where I like my
scoopability to be. Minus4 is Celsius is
a really good serving point for ice
cream. You can you can take it out of
the freezer, scoop it straight away.
Again, we've got a curve here,
but you can kind of ignore that if you
just go for your serving temperature of
about -14. -3 -4. That's a really nice
serving temperature. So, here's our
nutritional value. Again, we're we're
pretty much done. I can show you this
multiple times in every videos. We can
save this recipe if you want to. I mean,
it's basically just sweet cream. So,
let's type that in. And it needs a
desri. Well, it doesn't need a
description. It's an optional
description. So, let's put in it's ice
cream in it. There we go. That is what
we're going to call this ice cream.
We're going to save that. And let's copy
our amounts here. There we go. On our
ingredient side on the left, we can
literally just drag over, copy. So,
again, it's a really easy way to create
a balanced kind of recipe. The solids
are quite low or low for me. I like my
solids to be like I said 40%. But we're
using alo. So alo has a much higher
effect on a freezing point. So we have
to use less. That is where a lot of
solids come from in our recipes. Sugar.
Um the the use of a stabilizer to
counter that is really quite important
to create a luxury ice cream. So we're
going through all the effort of creating
a super nice sweet cream recipe, but
it's low in solids. So, we need to boost
those solids back up by imitating that
with the stabilizer and then cooking it
slightly to reduce the water content
which will naturally increase our
solids. You could emit the stabilizer
and cook it down more. Cook it down 5 6
7%. You will naturally increase the
percentage of solids based on your
recipe because you're evaporating water
which is an empty ingredient. So, that's
another way to to do that. It's
there are other ways. There are other
things in this calculator such as adding
ingredients. If you want me to show you
how to add ingredients in there, let me
know in the comments and I'll do it in
another video in a few weeks. Um, but
for now, let's just drink the coffee and
make our recipe. Right, we got all our
ingredients. Super simple recipe. Like I
said, this is the alilos I'm using this
time. Stock levels seem to fluctuate in
the US, so I just get what's cheapest.
This is powdered rather than granulated.
Doesn't make any difference. So, let's
get everything in. Let's start with our
milk. And there's 634 g. Into that goes
634 g of our cream. 33% whipping cream.
Into that, we're going to have 25 g of
glucose syrup or straight corn syrup.
Again, I I keep having to say this, this
is not high fructose corn syrup. Don't
over complicate it. 25 grams. 70 g of
skimm milk powder. And now we're going
to do our alulos. We're going to do that
separately cuz we're using a stabilizer.
Okay. 135 g of our powdered alos. And
into the alios, we're going to put 1.9 g
of our stabilizer. It really does make a
difference in recipes that are lower in
solids than you'd like. That increased
viscosity really does help create a more
balanced mouth fill. Our sugar can go
into our ice cream base. Stir this
together. And let's get this on heat.
Going to heat this up to 85C, 185F. And
that's because we've got that stabilizer
in it. If you don't use your stabilizer,
the result won't be as good, but it will
still be delicious cuz it's high fat.
15% just shy. And then we'll come back.
There we go. 85C.
Doesn't take long, you know, depending
how fast you heat it up. 5 10 minutes,
something like that. So, we're going to
let this cool down in the refrigerator.
Going to age this overnight. And that
just allows the milk flavors to build
within that base. And it also allows the
stabilizer to itself distribute in
amongst the base properly. So, in that
goes, let's talk about our cherry swirl.
For the cherry syrup, there are a few
ways to do this. You can buy it. You can
use a coffee syrup, and I've done that
before. Amarina cherry syrup. That's
delicious. Um, but today we're going to
use a can of Bing cherries in syrup.
This is a 400ml
can. And importantly, it has 42 g of
sugar per 167 ml. That tells us what we
need to do to this. So, let's open this
can. We're going to pour the whole thing
into a pan. Now, we're going to put this
on a gentle heat. Get it up to 85 90
centrade and leave it there for about 5
or 10 minutes. And we're going to reduce
the weight by about 30 to 40%. We got a
reduction of about 30% of the water
content in our cherries. We're going to
leave this here now to cool down for
about half an hour because we're going
to blend them in a blender. You can use
a stick blender or a food processor or
anything. So, if you've got one of
those, get it ready and then we're going
to carry on. Let's pour them into here.
So, with those cherries in there, we've
got our corn syrup or glucose and normal
sugar. Let's blend these up nice and
smooth. You could absolutely strain
this, but I want this a pretty natural
kind of cherry swirl. Want a natural
cherry color and everything. So, with
that in there, we can now add in 25 g of
glucose or corn syrup and 10 g of normal
sugar. The normal sugar is there to
adjust the sweetness level and obviously
the freezing point depression. And the
glucose syrup is there to change the
texture and to affect the way the ice
crystals form in this so that we don't
get a super icy kind of cherry swirl. So
with that in mind, let's get a little
spatula. It's like a spatulette
and stir that together. And it's going
to go back on heat again. We're going to
heat this up to 85 C and keep it there
for 2 minutes. So let's do that. And
that is now also going to go in the
fridge overnight to let that flavor
develop. and for it to thicken up. This
is a natural cherry swirl. So, I
actually quite like the unnatural cherry
swirl. So, before we pre-chaw our
machine, just going to explain what's
going to happen. Going to get the ice
cream base in there. Going to take it
out of the fridge, stir it up, and then
get it in here cooling down. Whilst
that's happening, we're going to take
our chocolate out the freezer because I
wanted to keep that in the freezer.
Stops a lot of the static making your
chocolate fly everywhere. chop that up
before we put it in. And then we'll get
our cherry swirl out as well. So, let's
get all of that going.
Heat. Heat.
Black Forest ice cream with sweet cream
base chocolate addins. Not a stretchella
cuz we're not adding it in while it's
freezing. So, it's basically just
chopped chocolate. And then that more
natural cherry swirl. Let's try some.
See how this turned out.
I don't normally make sweet cream bases
and I definitely don't make fuel lattes
gelato um because I like my ice cream to
taste something. But occasionally
there's a situation where you want the
add-ins to kind of shine forward. And
that's what we got here. We got uh
basically an unflavored milkflavored if
you will ice cream base. Really nice
mouth feel. Higher fat, 15%. Or was it
14%? I forget. Higher fat levels. You
can taste that chocolate. You can taste
that cherry without the cherry going
artificial. I like using this as
a cherry swirl. You can thicken it up
with a little bit of go or zantham,
whatever.
Um, but this is uh super super nice.
Much stronger flavor than this cherry
swirl. This being natural, this has been
concentrated and has additional flavor
boosters into it. But I love this stuff.
So, there we go. Uh, using an ice cream
calculator or using scupulator
specifically to do this one. There's a
lot more that you can do on these ice
cream calculators. I'm just on these
videos. cuz I just kind of touch in how
to add the ingredients and look at how
to balance a recipe. But
it a full instructional video on how to
use an ice cream calculator, whether
that be scoop later or the super complex
ones like Patrick's ice cream
calculator, then those kind of videos
are going to be, you know, half an hour
long plus. So, if you do want a video
like that, and I know a lot of you
won't, but let me know in the comments
if you want me to do an elongated video
on the interesties, adding recipes,
adding ingredients,
where you should be concentrating your
percentages on, balancing gelatoes and
ice creams and sorbets, etc. It's it's a
super complex video, so it would take a
long time to film, so I'm only going to
do it if there's enough demand for it.
So, do let me know in the comments.
Don't forget to like and subscribe and I
will see you next week when I make
something. I haven't figured that out
yet. So,
bye.